<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plea for free-mens liberties: or The monopoly of the Eastland marchants anatomized by divers arguments (wch will also serve to set forth the unjustnesse of the marchant-adventurers monopoly,) and proved illegall, unnaturall, irrationall, against the honour of the nation, tending to its ruine and vassalage, procured by evill counsellors: and lastly treasonable: with a short comment upon their oath, worthy of every mans serious perusall. / Penned for the publique good, by Thomas Johnson marchant.</title>
            <author>Johnson, Thomas, marchant.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87610</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J850</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E319_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200551</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861268</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861268</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113399</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87610)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113399)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 52:E319[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plea for free-mens liberties: or The monopoly of the Eastland marchants anatomized by divers arguments (wch will also serve to set forth the unjustnesse of the marchant-adventurers monopoly,) and proved illegall, unnaturall, irrationall, against the honour of the nation, tending to its ruine and vassalage, procured by evill counsellors: and lastly treasonable: with a short comment upon their oath, worthy of every mans serious perusall. / Penned for the publique good, by Thomas Johnson marchant.</title>
                  <author>Johnson, Thomas, marchant.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed Anno 1646. and are to be sold in London, at every stationers shop, that loves liberty, and hates monopolies,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 26 1645"; the second 6 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Eastland Company --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Monopolies --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:113399:1"/>
            <head>The Prologue to all the Commons of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVOrthy Freemen of <hi>England,</hi> the former publique Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of this Kingdom, by their Machivilian empoyſened principles, and ſpecious pretences of common good, whereas nothing leſſe was intended, have moſt cunningly and fraudently cozened you of your native freedoms, to which by the fundamentall lawes and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Kingdom, yee were born unto, &amp; ſecretly by wicked patents have ſtolne away your Birth-right, to ſet up the particular and ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of private ſocieties: One of which <hi>I</hi> here preſent to your ſerious conſideration, as a great grievance and burthen under which the honeſt Clothier eſpecially, and thouſands of poore people groane: yee know for what this Kingdom hath almoſt been waſted to aſhes, yee have ſpent ſo much of your eſtates and blood, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſubjects liberty, to which all civil government is ſubſervient. My advice to all is this, eſpecially the clothiers and others, who are deeply intereſſed, that as they love their bleeding dying Country, their deliverance from ſo great a thraldome, they would by petitioning, and all lawfull means, be earneſt with the Parliament, for the removall of this and all other preſſures. They are bound in duty to God, in juſtice to you, in diſchargall of ſo great a truſt committed into their hands, to eaſe you of all unjuſt grievances, intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable burthens, be therefore active in the work. For very importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſake, your indeavours will be crowned with a happy ſucceſſes and (if you faint not) reap the benefit of your labors, which ſhall alwaies be the deſire of him who is willing to ſerve you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Johnſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:113399:1"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoſoever ſurvayes this Iland in her radiant and ſhining luſtre with community and freedom, cannot but ſay, <hi>o quanta mutatio!</hi> oh how great a change! for indeed, this Kingdom is a corporation or ſociety of men under one form of civil government, made by common conſent in Parliament, who are all bound by the law, to maintain common freedom, and the generall good of each other.</p>
            <p>But particulars, Patent ſocieties ſwelling with a luciferian ſpirit, in deſiring to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance into a higher room then their fellows, did by ſeruptitious Patents incorporate themſelves, excluſively became deſtructive to the whole body, and ſubverters of the true ancient priviledges of the people, and of all ſocieties, thoſe of Marchants are the worſt, having no foundation on the lawes; The fellowſhip and charter of thoſe that ſtile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Marchants of Eaſt-land, is a monopoly of this kind, according to the true genuine ſence of the word monopoly, relating to a private company, who aſcribe unto themſelves the ſole exerciſe and benefit of ſuch a trade, wherein every ſubject hath equall freedome with them, all which this monopoly doth, and is illegal, being contrary to <hi>magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> the petition of right, Statutes of monopolics, with divers others, and in particular theſe 3. following: 1. is of the 14. of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Item,</hi> Where it is contained in the great Charter, that all Marchants ſhall have ſafe and ſure conduct to go out of the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and to come, and abide, and go through the Realme of <hi>England:</hi> aſwell by water as by land: we at the requeſt of the Prelates, Earles, Barons, and Commons, will and grant for us, and for our heirs and ſucceſſors, that all Mirchants, Denizens, and Foraigners (except thoſe which be of our enmity) may without let, ſafely come into the ſaid Realme of <hi>England,</hi> with their goods and Marchandize, and ſafely tarry and ſafely return, paying the cuſtoms, ſubſidies, and other profits reaſonably thereof due, ſo alwaies, that franchiſe and free cuſtomes reaſonably, granted by us and our anceſtors to the City of <hi>London,</hi> and other cities and good Townes of our Realm of <hi>England,</hi> be to them ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. The 2. is of 18. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.3. That the ordinance made before this time, upon taking of ſorts of wools in every County, be wholy nulled and defeated, and that every man, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well ſtranger as privy from henceforth may buy wool, according as they may agree with the ſeller, as they were wont to do, before the ſaid ordinances, and that the ſea be open to all manner of marchants, to paſſe with their marchandize where it ſhall pleaſe them. By both theſe ſtatutes it evidently appeareth, that every Engliſhman may tranſport his commodity without moleſtation, to what port beyond ſea he pleaſeth, and make ſale for his beſt advantage, every Engliſhman being a native denizen and privy man of this kingdom, according to the true meaning of the ſaw: for it is imaginable to me, that the law ſhould provide better for aliens, then her own children; the 3. is of 12. <hi>H.</hi> 7.6. <hi>viz.</hi> as followeth To the diſcreet Commons in this preſent Parl ſheweth unto your diſcreet wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, the Marchant Adventurers inhabiting and dwelling in divers ports of this Realm out of the City of <hi>London,</hi> that where they have their paſſage, reſort, courſe and recourſe with their goods, wares, and marchandize in divers coaſts and parts beyond the ſea, aſwel into <hi>Spain, Portugal, Britan, Ireland, Normandy, France, Civil, Venice, Danſk, Eaſtland, Freezeland,</hi> and other divers and many places, regions and countries being in league and amity with the King our ſoveraign Lord, there to buy and ſell; and make their exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges with the ſaid goods, wares, and marchandizes, according to the law and cuſtom uſed in every of the ſaid regions and places, and there every perſon freely to uſe himſelf to his moſt advantage, without exaction, fine, impoſition, or contribution to be had or taken of them, to, for, or by any Engliſh perſon or perſons. &amp;c. By which Statute, all marchants, aſwell thoſe inhabiting in divers parts of the Kingdoms, as of the city of <hi>London,</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo every free born ſubject, is acknowledged as his right to have freedom to trade to the
<pb facs="tcp:113399:2"/>ſaid parts mentioned, and to divers other regions and countries without ſubjection to any patent or paying any exaction, fine, &amp;c. for in that the ſtatute ſaith, every perſon is freely to uſe himſelf to his moſt advantage, without exaction, &amp;c. to be had or taken of them, or any of them, to, for, or by any Engliſh perſon, or perſons, it clearly holds forth, that the marchant, and conſequently every man that uſeth comerce to theſe parts, ought not to come under the obedience of any opreſſing corporation whatſoever: now <hi>Danſt</hi> and the <hi>Eaſt-land</hi> being expreſſed in the ſtatute, which are the principall parts to which theſe <hi>Eaſtland</hi> marchants are priviledged by their monopoly, and indeed the crown and glory of the reſt for venting our native commodities, as alſo the other included, when the ſtitute ſaith, and other divers and many places, regions, and countries, I hope every ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man will be willing with heart and hand to endevour the recovery of our birthright which the law ſo evidently makes out owne from theſe unjuſt oppreſſors.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Contrary to the light of nature, which teacheth men to walk by congruity and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality, not to oppreſſe, becauſe they would not be oppreſſed, not to take away any mans right, becauſe they would not have another uſe the ſame meaſure to them. Which prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of nature are engraven upon the hearts of heathens, who certainly will riſe up in judgement one day againſt theſe men that ſell us for ſlaves in our own land.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is irrationall, reaſon being the fountain of all honeſt laws, gives to every man pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety and liberty: propriety of intereſt, freedom of enjoyment and improovement to his own advantage, from that propriety take away freedom, &amp; a conſiderable part is gone nay we ſee it by experience, that thoſe who have bereft us of our liberty, have made bold with our propriety, and indeed if prerogative may take away the one, why not the other from the ſame principles? ſo that it appears to be rationall, that every native who hath propriety of goods, wares, and marchandize, hath freedom to tranſport them to any port beyond Seas, and there convert them, to his own profit, it being his true and proper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance ſo to do, it is very ſtrange to my underſtanding, that one man ſhould do the work, and another man receive the wages, I mean, that the honeſt clothier who has toyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much in the making of his cloth, ſhall not have the benefit to ſell it here for his own gain, or to ſhip it for more profit, but being debared of freedom in both, muſt make ſale to them, in whoſe power it is to give him what price they pleaſe, whereby he is cheated of the fruit of his labour.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the monopoly is againſt the honour of the Nation, becauſe by it the people are put in acondition of vaſſalage in their own country, it takes away induſtry the ſpring of wealth, the hearts of the people being brought to ſervility, and not able by reaſon of this, and other the like patents, to imploy themſelves, cannot chuſe but procure ſad effects if not timely prevented, for</p>
            <p n="5">5. The pattent was illegally procured by the ſolicitation of evil Counſellors, under the broad ſeal of <hi>England,</hi> in the 25 year of the raigne of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> it being of no longer ſtanding under ſpecious pretences, as the profit of her then Majeſty, the good of the Kingdom, &amp;c. whereas by it the natives have bin weakned and ſpoiled, which will eaſily appear, if we conſider theſe particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By reaſon of this patent, thouſands of poor people are in a condition of beggery, who otherwiſe might maintain themſelves in honeſt callings, by the making of cloath, and other woolen manufactures, by carding, ſpinning, weaving, &amp;c. and certainly this one thing throughly conſidered, ſhould ſtir up the bowels of every truly noble ſpirited Engliſhman, to double his ſtrength, if it were poſſible, an hundred fold, in all juſt waies, for the removall of ſo great an obſtruction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The poor Clothier ſuppreſſed, none being to trade to thoſe parts but the company, the clothier makes not half the cloaths he might; and for thoſe he doth make, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:113399:2"/>of a confederacy, and having all the priviledge of buying in their own hands, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof, many times he is forced to fell them at a far leſſ. price then they coſt him in making, or elſe to keep them till the next year, which diſcourages and ſlackens the clothier in the proſecution of his calling, and cauſeth ſome to fail, others to give over, and thoſe which remain, many of them ſcarce can make a living.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Monopoly greatly impareth the trade of cloth, thoſe who are judicious affirm that 5000 cloths more then are, would be made, ſhipped, and expended yearly in thoſe parts to which they are authoriſed to trade to, which I verily beleeve &amp; prove thus, all the cloth they ſhip, ſome extraordinary times excepted, is but to 1. or 2. Towns, and there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding their Factors, who making ſale to the Binger, he ſendeth the cloth up and down the Country, from whence ariſeth many miſchiefes, the Countries not being furniſhed as they ſhould: as alſo the ſelling at ſuch exceſſive rates, cauſeth the Datch to make cloth in an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant manner, &amp; to be ſatisfied with it, though it be exceeding courſe: and again, there being divers Kingdoms, Dominions, Dukedoms, Countries, Cities, and Towns, to which by their patent they are licenſed, what advantage would the young marchant have, having ſo vaſt a compaſſe, how active would he be from Town to Town, from City to City, from one Country to another, and ſelling cheap, would invite forraign parties to ſet a true eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate upon our native commodities, and certainly were trade free, <hi>Sweedland,</hi> and <hi>Pomer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> would vent much cloth, whereas the company is not able to ſatisfie the <hi>Eaſtland</hi> it ſelf, by reaſon of the ſmalneſſe of their ſtock, it may be eaſily conceived, that ſuch a ſmall Company of private men, are never able to ſuffice ſuch famous Kingdoms and Dukedoms to which they onely are licenced to traffick.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It cauſeth a great decay of Navigation, which ſuſtaineth the mariners, ſo that by this and other the like patents, the ſaylor is greatly ſuppreſt.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It obſtructeth returns, divers of the moſt ſtable commodities which our Country ſtands in, need of, are imported by them, viz. flax, hemp, pot-aſhes, pitch, tar, courſe linnen, packing, canvas, with divers other very conſiderable marchandize, now they bring over when they pleaſe, and what they pleaſe, and ſell at what price they pleaſe, which cannos but have ſundry evil concomitance. 1. Our Country is not ſatisfyed with that variety and conveniency it ſhould: and 2. By reaſon the Citizen gives ſuch an unreaſonable rate to the marchant, the poor have all exceſſive dear, giving many times half as much more then the comodity is worth, or then it would be ſold for were the trade but open, from which and ſuch other dealings it is, that the people are unconſcionably waſted, and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and therefore what ere it coſt us, lets have this ravenous patent down, whereby there would be all theſe gallant effects: multitudes of poor maintained, the clothier raiſed, the trade of cloth greatly augmented, by reaſon that thouſands might be vented more, then are the number of marchants increaſed, the art of navigation furthered, and laſtly, an univerſal benefit to the whole nation, from the plenty of marchandize imported, which we ſhould have at far eaſier and more valuable conſiderations. <hi>Ob.</hi> But if trade be free, the Alien will expect freedom alſo. <hi>An</hi> I ſee no ground but aliens paying cuſtom, provided alwaies that wee enjoy as full and large priviledges with them, they ought to have the like here with us. but 2. ſuppoſe the State ſhould prohibit ſtrangers, yet there is no ſhadow or colour of right reaſon, that we who have equall liberties in the lawes, have ventures our eſtates and lives ſo freely to preſerve them, ſhould be deprived of our true inheritance, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for further ſatisfaction, I ſhall here inſert part of their charter, that every one may judg whether it be juſt or no: Foraſmuch as we be credibly informed &amp;c. that you our Subjects marchants, and others, exerciſing and uſing the trafficque and feat of marchandize, out and from any our Dominions through the <hi>Sound,</hi> into the Realmes, Kingdoms, Dominions, Dukedome, Countries, Cities and Towns, of <hi>Norway, Swethia, Poland,</hi> and the territories of the ſame Kingdoms, as alſo into <hi>Letto,</hi> and <hi>Liefland,</hi> under the dominion of the King of
<pb facs="tcp:113399:3"/>
               <hi>Poall, Pruſſia,</hi> and alſo <hi>Pomerland,</hi> from the river of <hi>Odera</hi> Eaſtward, and alſo <hi>Ry</hi> and <hi>Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> in <hi>Lieſland</hi> aforeſaid <hi>Kingſbrough, Elbinge, Brownſbrough,</hi> and <hi>Danſick</hi> in <hi>Bruſia, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penhiven,</hi> and <hi>Elſenore</hi> in <hi>Danſk,</hi> except the <hi>Nerve,</hi> and the territories thereof belongings as alſo into the Iland of <hi>Finland, Goteland, Eweland,</hi> and <hi>Berntholme,</hi> within the <hi>Sound</hi> aforeſaid, by one conſent are willing to gather, congregate, and aſſemble your ſelves into one followſhip, and to be one body incorporate and politique, in deed, and in name; we conſidering that your purpoſes in this behalf are very laudable, do therefore not onely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and fanſie the ſame, but will you to perſevere in your good minds and purpoſes, to the eſtabliſhment and perfection thereof, and earneſtly deſiring that our marchants and their ſucceſſors haunting the ſaid Kingdoms, Dominions, Countries, Cities, and Townes, before mentioned, or any of them, for marchandize, in and through the <hi>Sound</hi> of the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark</hi> (except before excepted) may from hence forth profit and increaſe as proſperouſly a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any marchants of this Land have aforetime increaſed and prohibited, &amp; do grant for us, our heirs, and ſucceſſors that from hence forth there be and ſhall be, of the ſaid Fellowſhip, one Governour, and one Deputy, or Deputies, and foure and twenty aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the ſaid fellowſhip; and that they, or the major part of them, may make ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, Lawes, and ordinances: and that the aforeſaid Governour, or Deputie, or Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and their ſucceſſors, or the major part of them, as is aforeſaid then preſent, as often as need ſhall bee; the ſaid Statutes, Laws, and ordinances, ſhall and may execute and put in execution aſwell within our Realme of <hi>England,</hi> as within the ſaid Realmes, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, Cities, and Countries, and every of them: and for that divers perſons, our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, being not brought up in marchandize through their ignorance and lack of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, commit many inconveniency, we willing to reſiſt and prevent them, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to further the expert merchant in their lawfull and honeſt trade: will, and by our Regall Authority we Command, and alſo prohibite and forbid by theſe preſents, that no ſubject of us, our heirs, or ſucceſſors, which is not, nor ſhall bee by force of theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents made free of the ſaid Felloſhip ſhall by any manner of meanes at any time hereafter inter meddle in the trade of Marchandize; or by any meanes buy and ſell, or uſe any traffique into the ſaid parts of <hi>Eaſtland,</hi> and Countries aforeſaid, or any of them, (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept before excepted,) upon pain to incur our indignation: as alſo to pay ſuch fines, and emercements, and to ſuffer impriſonment, and ſuch other paines due to the Tranſgreſſors of the ſaid ſttatutes, ordinances, and conſtitutions of the ſaid Fellowſhip, or to the ſaid Governour or his Deputy and aſſiſtants aforeſaid, ſhall ſeeme meete and convenient, any Law, Statute, Cuſtome, or Ordinance, to the contrary thereof, many other things not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And do further by theſe preſents inhibit and forbid, all and every our ſubjects, and the ſubjects of us our heires and ſucceſſors, not being licenced and authorized by vertue of thoſe preſents, to traffique in and to the ſaid Countries, Kingdoms, Towns and places before recited, or uſe any manner of trade in and to them, contrary to the tenor of theſe preſents, upon pain to incurre the diſpleaſure of us, our heires and ſucceſſors, and to be fined, payned, and impriſoned, according to the ſeverall diſcretions and laws of the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the ſaid former ſeverall Companies and their ſucceſſors, witneſſe our ſelf at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> the 17. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in the 21. year of our Raigne.</p>
            <p>I no ſooner made a ſurveyal of this cruel engine, what intollerable breaches &amp; inrodes it hath continually made upon us, but was caſt into a ſudden admiration, that ſo free a people as <hi>England,</hi> ſhould ſuffer themſelves ſo violently to be grownd to powder, which I ſhall illuſtrate to be treaſonable in the practiſers of it by theſe poſitions: 1. If to ſurrender a Caſtle by the Captain of that Caſtle through fear and cowardize, and not from any compliance with the enemy be treaſon, as was adjudged in the Parliament 1. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. then is this a treaſonable patent, for beſides the place, there is onely a loſſe of the adjacent
<pb facs="tcp:113399:3"/>parts, but by this patent our lawes, liberties, nay our very lives, in purſuance of both the former, are ſubjected to will and tyranny, he that walks in the exerciſe of freedom, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to law, is ſubject to their counter commands, and to be fined, payned, and impriſoned and to ſuffer ſuch other puniſhments as to them ſhall ſeem meet and convenient.</p>
            <p>If to kill a judg upon the bench be treaſon, becauſe of malice, not to the perſon, but to the law, then is this a treaſonable patent, here is not onely a malice to the law, but a moſt butcherly weapon killing and deſtroying of it, theſe 2. cannot dwell together, for the life of the patent, ſo far as it extends, is the death of the law, which ſtops its free courſe for the benefit of the people, and makes it meerly a dead letter, a carkas without a ſoul, a power being given to Mr. Governour and his companions, to make laws, ſtatutes, and ordinances which power is more and far greater then belongs to the chief magiſtrate to give, or can legally or juſtly be exerciſed by any but the Parliament, and therefore not to be received by any perſon or perſons whatſoever, and certainly thoſe laws, and all that government derived from Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> broad ſeal commiſſion are according to the luſts of theſe men, being extrajuditiall, in that they are above the ſphaere of the law. 2. Contrary to the law, if the endeavouring the ſubverſion of the ancient fundamentall lawes and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Kingdom, and to introduce an arbitrary and tyrannical government be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: as was adjudged in the caſe of the Earle of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and in the caſe of Sir <hi>Robert Berkley,</hi> by the firſt article of impeachment by the Houſe of Commons, <hi>Iuly</hi> 6. 1641. then is this a treaſonable patent, for here is not onely an indevour, but an actuall ſurrender of both law and government, which have made <hi>England</hi> a free people, and what more anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent or fundamental, then thoſe laws which gratify the Commons; and by which they injoy their very lives, here is an arbitrary government introduced, &amp; put into the hands of thoſe whom the ſubject doth not own to have any right of power and rule, and that in ſo high a nature as can be no leſſe then monarchicall, for what can a monarchicall power be, but to make lawes, and to puniſh the tranſgreſſors according to thoſe lawes, by confiſcation of goods, impriſonment, or taking away the life of the vaſſals, all which they may doe by their patent, and certainly this company of Marchants of <hi>Eaſt-land,</hi> who have practized arbitrarily for ſo long a time as they have done, againſt the liberties of the natives deſerve for all their cruelties to be proceeded againſt as publique delinquents to the State.</p>
            <p>As touching their oath, it is one of the worſt (I am confident) that ever was made, which I ſhall here inſert for every mans knowledge. You ſhall ſwear to be good and true to out Soveraign Lord the Kings Majeſty, and to his Heir as and Succeſſors, you ſhall bee obedient and aſſiſtant to Mr. Governour, his Deputy, and Deputies, and aſſiſtants of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of <hi>Eaſtland,</hi> all ſtatutes and ordinances which bee, or ſhall be made by the ſaid Governour, or by his deputies, and aſſiſtants ſtanding in force, you ſhall truly hold and keep, having no ſingular regard to your ſelf, in hurt or prejudice of the common-weal of the ſaid fellowſhip, you ſhall heal, and not bewray, and if you ſhall know any manner of perſon or perſons which intend any hurt, harm, or prejudice to our ſaid Soveraign Lord the Kings Majeſty, or unto his land, or to the foreſaid fellowſhip or priviledges of the ſame you ſhall give knowledge thereof, and do it to be known to the ſaid Governour or his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty, and you ſhall not colour or free any Forraigners goods not free of the ſaid fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, all which you ſhall hold and keep to the uttermoſt of your power, or elſe being juſtly condemned for making default in any of the premiſes, you ſhall truly from time to time, being orderly demanded, content and pay to the treaſurer of this Company for the time being, all and every ſuch mulcts and penalties which have beene or ſhall be limitted and ſet for the tranſgreſſors of the ſame. <hi>So God you help.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lieutenant Col. <hi>Lilburn</hi> in his late book called <hi>Innocency and Truth juſtified,</hi> being an
<pb facs="tcp:113399:4"/>anſwer to Mr. <hi>Prius</hi> look, called <hi>the lyar confounded,</hi> hath theſe paſſages, pag. 53. And i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſecond place, ſeeing they know, <hi>viz.</hi> the marchant adventurers, that the Petition o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Right doth condemn the King and his Privie Counſell for making and adminiſtring o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> oaths, not made by common conſent in Parliament, and ſeeing the Parliament us they ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well know, was lately ſo angry at the Biſhops, and their convocation, for aſſuming to themſelves the boldnes to make an oath, although they were inveſted with a more colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable authority to juſtify them therein, then theſe can pretend, how exemplary ought the puniſhment of theſe men to be for their impudence and boldnes, after the knowledge of all this, to force and preſſe upon the freemen of <hi>England,</hi> an oath of their own framing and making, and to keep their freedoms from them, becauſe out of Conſcience they dar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not take them, which at this preſent day is the condition of one Mr. <hi>Iohnſon,</hi> late ſervant to Mr <hi>Whitlock,</hi> one of the Eaſt Country Monopolizing Marchants, which is all one in nature with the Monopoly of Marchant Adventurers: And not onely do they moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly keep my freedom from me, for which I have ſo often ventured my life in the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern ſervice according to the Cuſtome of the City of <hi>London,</hi> but moſt inhumanely have taken from me my place of Factorſhip in the <hi>Eaſtland,</hi> and all becauſe I have reiected thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> monopoly and diabolicall oath, and this was the gallam ſervice of Mr. <hi>Burnell</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and his aſſociates, the 3. <hi>Octob.</hi> 1645. but I expect to ſee Juſtice (that baniſhed exile return in all her glory, and theſe oppreſſing task maſters called to a iuſt account: for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain I am, that the law never gave them authority to make an oath, or to force it upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> conſcience; beſides the oath containeth many perjuries, in the ſecond branch it ties the ſwearer to be aſſiſtant to Mr. Governour and his confederates in all their diſhoneſt procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. In the third branch, to keep all their pernitious laws and ordinances, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ordinances are to deprive the Subiect of his right, and this will not ſatisfie, but to all that are to be made, O intollerable burthen! whither will this bottomleſſe pit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> is &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. and innumerable company of &amp;c. In the fourth branch, to keep all the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> cozening ſecrets and underhand dealings in the purſuance of their patent. And in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> branch, for making default in any of the premiſes, that is, for forſwearing himſelf, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he doth that keeps it, aſwell as he that keeps it not, becauſe he ſwears not in truth, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and in righteouſnes, to pay ſuch mulcts and penalties which have been or ſhall be limitted and ſet for the tranſgreſſors of the ſame, as if ſuch great crimes could be waſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> away with a pennance: for my part I am clear in this point, that whoſoever he be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bends &amp; yeelds obedience to this or the like oath, deſerve not the name of an Engliſhman ſurely their deſignes are to uſe the expreſſion of Lieu. Col. <hi>Lilburn,</hi> in p. the 54 of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpeaking againſt the marchant adventurers, to make <hi>England</hi> a land of ſlavery, ignoran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and beggery, or elſe a land of perjury: I have now learned the meaning of that Scripture <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.16.17 <hi>And he cauſeth all both ſmall and great, rich and poor, free and boun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to receive a mark in their right hand, or in their foreheads that none might buy or ſell, ſave be that had the mark, or the name of the beaſt, or the number of his name:</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates as I conceive to all monopolies whatſoever, <hi>ſublat a cauſa tollitur effectus</hi> take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way theſe marchants patents, and all other of the like nature, and there will a ſudden <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> appear to the relief of the honeſt, comfort and tranquility to the whole Nation for the effecting whereof, if I ſhall but erritate the curteous Reader, it is price ſufficient for him whoſe deſire it is not to live, but in the truth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
